today we're going to talk about Optical
stimulation of mitochondria reduces
blood glucose levels let's talk about
this article that was just published on
August
28th on this website that actually
carries non- peerreview literature which
is still the situation here so why I
bring this up today is because I want to
talk a little bit more about light and
diabetes a lot of times people think
that diabetes
is
simply the end result of just diet but
in fact diabetes is a multifaceted
disease unfortunately or fortunately
depending how you want to look at it and
a lot of things like
exercise and activity can be helpful as
well as exposure to sunlight so we're
going to talk about that here now before
we do that we have to talk a little bit
about the mitochondria
so inside each
cell is a nucleus but there's also these
tiny little
organel called
mitochondria and they are the parts of
the cell that produce
energy in the form of
ATP and the way they do that is by
breaking
down uh fats
sugars and
proteins so these things go
into these little mitochondria and out
com something called
ATP which is
energy also what comes out is carbon
dioxide what we want to look at today is
see how Optical
stimulation of
cells can actually change that actually
what we'll see is potentially going up
on ATP and as you start to use these
things they start to go down and
specifically we're going to look at
blood sugars which has to do with that
so this looks like a really busy slide
but I want you
to just bear with me on this okay so
here we have the
mitochondria and that's this thing right
here okay and as I said there's fats
and
proteins but we're going to talk about
sugar and that's glucose right there so
glucose is broken down in the
cell should be a y
to different intermediates and it
basically goes through the
mitochondrian through this something
called the citric acid cycle and it
makes these reducing agents and then it
goes to this part of the mitochondrian
but what comes out is basically as we
said here a
ATP but I want you to notice something
obviously we have oxygen going in that's
why we need to breathe it's because
oxygen is necessary for all this to
happen but notice here carbon dioxide is
a
byproduct okay keep that in mind here's
the atps that are coming out that's the
energy oxygen is going into the system
carbon dioxide is coming out and that's
why we breathe in oxygen and we breathe
out carbon dioxide that's how we burn
energy to get this bur we burn fats
proteins and sugars to get uh
energy now what we're going to see here
is the scientist
hypothesize that light specifically red
light actually can penetrate down into
the water here that's surrounding this
pump that's making the ATP and it can
make it more effective so that it
actually work works better now of course
you can see what's going to happen if it
makes it work better is that the carbon
dioxide level should go up and the
glucose level should go
down Okay so let's take a look and see
if that
happens so we're going to go through the
study bit by bit so they say here in the
introduction that red
light
stimulates mitochondrial respiration
that's exactly what we were just talking
about shifting its metabolism and this
this is known as something called
photobiomodulation that's a longterm
look that up and you'll start to see
that a lot of people now are using
photobiomodulation for a lot of
different diseases including multiple
sclerosis including Alzheimer's disease
Parkinson's disease even long Co okay so
light specifically red light at this
wavelength Alters cellular respiratory
rate increases membrane potentials ATP
production and and reduces this reactive
stress and inflammatory markers so
they're basically saying here that light
is really important for your
health this results in improved sensory
and motor function including aged human
color perception that means people who
are older can actually see better when
they are exposed to Red
Light even in the near infrared
spectrum they say here that the
nanoscopic interfacial water layer
surrounding the pumps that we were
talking about actually improves when
there are energy transferred to that
water
becomes less viscous allowing that
Rotator pump to achieve greater momentum
and increase ATP production so they say
an increase in ATP production requires
more fuel since glucose is the primary
fuel in animals it they would think that
the glucose would actually go down and
these authors have already shown that in
bees okay so now they want to show it in
humans so that's what they tried to do
here to look for a non-invasive non-
pharmacutical way of dropping blood
sugars so what they did was they took 30
subjects and they randomize them that
means they put two groups in and this is
a great way of eliminating confounders
and biases is when you randomize there
was two groups there was a placebo group
and what we'll call the 670 group The
670 group is the group that's going to
get eventually exposed to red light at
670 nanometers so that's the wavelength
specifically okay Placebo on the left
and the 670 group on the right now what
they did next was they took a baseline
measurement in both groups without doing
anything so these should all have been
the same type of
thing and we'll call this
the no Placebo
ggt and the no 670 ggt what's a gtt gtt
is the glucose tolerance test so here in
the placebo group they didn't give them
any Placebo they just did a glucose
tolerance test and over here in the 670
group they did not give them any 670
okay so they're just sitting down in a
room and they're getting their blood
drawn after taking a a Bolis of glucose
as part of the glucose tolerance test
okay then what they did was they waited
no more than 7 days and they brought
them back in and this time in the 670
group they put this light on their back
that they could not see there were
goggles on and they shined 670 nmet
light on their back and then oh a short
time later about half an hour to an hour
later they measured the glucose
over here they did exactly the same
thing they strapped the thing on the
back they put goggles on but they just
didn't turn the light on that was the
only difference is they did not turn the
light on so you really have four groups
you have two two groups in the placebo
and you have two groups in the 670 let's
take a look now and see what
happened okay so here we are looking at
the placebo
versus the 670 which two are those we're
looking at this one versus this one and
we're trying to see here what this did
to glucose
notice that at three different
measurements after the glucose tolerance
test that started here at zero that at
about 45 minutes and 60 minutes and then
at 90 minutes there was a statistically
significantly lower blood
glucose and remember that each point
here is about 18 millgram per deciliter
okay this is a this is the European
system so just multiply this is above
the
Baseline notice how much above the
Baseline the blood sugar went for the
placebo in green and how much lower it
was just being exposed to light so what
is this telling you it's telling you
that light exposure can actually
mitigate super high blood sugars it'll
actually bring it down down if you
notice here at about 1 hour this was
about 2 points on this scale which would
be about 36 milligrams per deciliter
that's a quite a bit probably the uh
efficacy of a medication there all right
here's our group again let's take a look
now this time we're going to look
between these two groups and see what if
there was a difference remember they
just did a regular glucose tolerance
test by taking some glucose to see what
they did then they strapped this light
to the
back this device and they turned it on
okay so we're here we're seeing the full
measure of it and let's see what
happened again you can see statistically
significant differences along the way
that
670 was very beneficial compared to when
that same group did not put it on and
and turn it on all
right now what we're going to do is
we're going to look at these two
groups okay now this is without the
thing strapped to the back and this is
with it strapped to the back but with it
turned off okay there shouldn't be much
of a difference and sure enough there is
not much of a difference in fact none of
these points are statistically
significantly different from one
another all right and now finally let's
look at all four groups so here's the
maximum glucose level reached okay this
one is the placebo group that was on the
left this is the 670 NM group on the
right this one here is with just the
regular glucose tolerance
test and these here are after the lights
are strapped on notice that those two
are not different this one however is
different so what we found here is that
exposure just for 15 to 20 minutes this
light could actually mitigate the
increase in blood sugar so you may want
to consider this if you are eating maybe
eating outside eating around with a lot
of light these may be things that are
beneficial again this is a randomized
control trial so that's the highest
level of evidence and I think we're
going to talk a little bit more about
that coming up here shortly all right so
what we did here is we noticed that when
we sha
light on this area what happened was is
they believe that this became more
efficient and when it became more
efficient this cycle was able to spin
faster utilizing uh the products of
blood glucose which caused it to go down
now if that's the case we should notice
that there's an increase in carbon
dioxide let's take a look and see if
that was the case so again here's our
study design what we're going to do is
we're going to look at these two groups
here for measured carbon dioxide output
let's take a look here there really
wasn't any statistical significant
difference across the board that may
have been because of selection but
another way of looking at it would be to
look at it as this in the same group and
that's what they did so they're looking
at those in the intervention group that
didn't have anything on their back it
was just the glucose tolerance test
versus those that had it strapped onto
their back and turned on let's see what
happens there was one point there which
was statistically significant and that
was in the Light Group notice that there
was more not glucose but more entitle
CO2 that means that there is more carbon
dioxide being made in the middle of the
cell which is in the
mitochondria all right let's see if
there's any difference between these two
groups NOP no statistical significance
whatsoever so the conclusion of the
study is that
light given to the body and it's on the
order of being out in the sun for a few
minutes to 20 minutes to 30 minutes it's
unclear exactly how much you need but we
do know that red light in this Spectrum
which is visible seems to confer to the
body a switch in its ability to
metabolize glucose it increases its
ability to metabolize glucose and
therefore it causes the blood glucose
levels to go down so getting outside we
don't know how long this is going to
last for so if you go outside in the
morning before breakfast and turn on
these sensors to get your body able to
metabolize more and give more energy I
think you're going to actually have more
energy you'll have lower blood gluc
glucose levels and you'll feel better so
getting outside getting up in the
morning and getting that red light that
near infrared light too is going to be
better now that reminds me of a study
that we did looked at looking at this in
Europe so here was an interesting study
that they looked at the bright sunlight
and the cardi metabolic traits of two
European populationbased cohorts so they
did this study in Oxford England and
also in Leiden the Netherlands and the
total was about 13,000 subjects so it
was a big study and what they did was
they
tested their
blood on a particular day all throughout
the year but with each subject that came
in they looked at the weather report for
the previous seven days and they noted
how many half days of sun there were in
the previous s days and they noted that
there was an association between the
number of days that there was sun in the
previous
days and the Improvement in their
cardiovascular scores their diabetes
their score of diabetes insulin
resistance that the people that had more
sun had better metabolic
health so what's really interesting
about that is that this is something
that you can do almost immediately and
right away to get the full
benefit
of sunlight on your metabolic health
literally it could start today by making
changes in your lifestyle to making sure
that you're getting outside in the
morning if possible and getting some of
those Suns
rais so that it switches your
metabolism you know on our Channel we've
talked about long coid many people have
long coid and what they're showing here
is that people who have long
Co specifically these people over here
notice how it's red there but it's blue
over here by the arrow what that's
showing you is that all of these fatty
acid enzyme
metabolites are slowing down it seems in
Long Co which is PC what does this mean
this means that it seems as though
people with long coid tend to not be
able to metabolize fats as easily as
they did before they got Co some people
may notice that after Co it was was
harder to lose weight and it may be
because their mitochondria was
damaged what I would recommend if you
want to repair your mitochondria if you
want to get good mitochondria that's
very efficient and works very well
number one I would make sure to get
outside to get a wide swath of the
spectrum of the sun um to be able to do
its work that's number one okay number
two is you need new mitochondria if
you've damaged your old ones and the
best best way is to help your body
replace itself of the new mitochondria
so that happens at night when you're
sleeping but it will not happen if the
body has recently ingested a meal so
it's extremely important that you try to
have supper dinner very
early potentially before 6 o' so that
you are able to get in a fasting State
before you go to bed that's really
important uh to understand and uh this
is a long coid uh video that we actually
put to our website and to our YouTube uh
Channel called megc and it talks about
going through the research of this but
all to say is
that we know that long coid lack of
energy diabetes dementia Alzheimer's
disease have a rooting in problems with
the mitochondria and what we're saying
here is that light may be a real factor
and benefit uh in in terms of getting
over some of those diseases so the
bottom line here is it would be best to
get outside if you're concerned about
sunburn or skin cancer you can cover up
because this light the infrared light
specifically can penetrate through those
clothes but the best thing to do is to
get natural light especially in the
early morning hours when the sun is
coming up and in the late evening hours
because these are the hours where
ultraviolet radiation which causes the
skin cancer is at it
lowest and I hope this has been helpful
if you have any questions please send us
an emails text thanks for joining us for
True Health
Tuesdays